It only lasts 5 days per month, but
there's a growing body of literature
indicating that it has potent
anti-cancer effects. But is it even
worth it? And is it for people with
cancer as it is for people trying to
prevent cancer? I'm talking about, as
some of you might already be aware, the
FMD or fasting mimicking diet.
Essentially, it's a five-day diet that
is very low calorie and especially low
protein. It was popularized by a
researcher named Dr. Walter Longo and
some of my earlier content like uh this
firm six years ago covered some of the
early studies on FMD.
Good gracious
how things have changed for the better.
Moving on though, since then the early
days looking at mice and a small amount
in humans, there's been more evidence
that fasting mimicking diets do
translate to better cancer outcomes.
like here where cancer patients were
enrolled into a trial and randomized to
undergo a fasting mimicking diet every
month or not known as the control. If
the lines go to the right and stay
further up, that's a better cancer
outcome. Clearly, the FMD treated group
experience benefits in combating already
present cancer. In fact, some studies in
cancer patients have tried to tease out
why the FMD works. One reason is due to
significant reductions in cancer growth
signals like insulin associated
molecules if that's insulin itself or
IGF-1. So insulin like growth factor 1.
These molecules will when they're bound
to cells but certainly cancer cells
encourage growth signaling within the
cell. In the context of already rapidly
growing cancer cells that's disastrous.
So naturally reducing these molecules in
our blood can be important. The main
point here is that fasting mimicking
diet has clinical evidence indicating
its effectiveness against cancer. And
one of the mechanisms by which it does
that is by reducing the cancerpromoting
molecules in your blood like insulin and
IGF-1 as just a few examples. But that's
child's play because the FMD does much
more than that. In fact, in that same
study in cancer patients, FMD has been
shown to revitalize our immune system.
That means that the FMD reduces a
population of immunosuppressive cells,
essentially cells that reduce the
activity of the immune system and
increases the amount of cancer killing
cells. That leads to an overall shift of
a less hospitable environment for
cancer. Those cancer cells think that
they run this town. Well,
they ain't met this immune system. Then
a tumble weed goes by. Cancer draws its
colt 45, but an FMD stimulated immune
cell ain't called quick draw gym for no
reason. Now,
beyond the right beyond the
revitalization and reagression of the
immune system against cancer cells that
FMD can also force what's known as the
anti-warberg effect. Essentially a long
time time ago it was discovered that
many cancer cells prefer the use of
glucose so blood sugar as their main
source of energy. Because of this
preference many cancer cells do not use
their mitochondria for energy
production. They use what's known as
anorobic glycolysis to generate the
energy that they need to function in the
form of a molecule called ATP. The same
energy molecule that all our cells use.
This whole preference for glucose and
glycolysis for energy generation by
cancer cells is called the Warberg
effect. Now, something that many people
don't realize is that cancer cells don't
just prefer glucose for energy
generation, but to create substrate for
another important pathway called the
pentos phosphate pathway, which allows
cancer cells to grow at a faster rate
than normal. We won't go into the
specifics now, but the key point here is
that many cancer cells prefer using
blood glucose. Now, the FMD reduces
blood glucose, limiting the available
glucose in the blood for cancers to feed
on. So, what do cancer cells do? Well,
according to this review, the cancer
cells are forced to use the limited
glucose that they have to access to
generate as much energy as possible.
That means two things. One, mitochondria
become more active in cancer cells
because the mitochondria can produce
much more of that cellular energy out of
glucose than glycolysis alone can. Two,
less substrate is produced out of these
offshoot pathways like the
pentosphosphate pathway, limiting cancer
cell growth and the ability for cancer
cells to protect themselves. These two
forced cancer cell changes lead to a
slowing of cancer cell growth but also
cause more damage to the cancer cells
because as mitochondria are more active
they produce damaging molecules called
reactive oxygen species. This whole
process since it's the opposite of the
Warberg effect is called aptly named the
anti-Warberg effect. As a quick word,
there's much more complexity here with
exceptions to these rules, but for some
cancers, this is an additional way for
FMD to stress cancer cells.
The main point here is that a fasting
mimicking diet changes the immune
profile to be more anti-cancerous, as
well as forces some cancer cells to be
in a metabolically unfavorable position,
stressing them and reducing their
growth. All this is pretty impressive
research and there's plenty more on how
fasting mimicking diets affect cancer
like the impact on the microbiome and
cancer fighting something called a
starvation mediated escape pathway. I
discuss low carbohydrate diets in this
context and more. So if you're
interested in a deeper analysis of this
kind of stuff consider checking out the
Physionic Insiders. It's my premium
research platform where I upload the
extended version of this video that
you're watching along with an
accompanying article, actionable
takeaways, and speaking to that, I
designed a personalized fasting
mimicking diet calculator and sample
program for the insiders. If you're
interested in trying the FMD for
yourself without the hassle of figuring
out if you're doing it correctly, then
check out the insiders. You also get
access to all these perks. The link is
in the description. Now to context and
how can we use this all? Well, three
critical pieces of context here. One, in
the clinical trials, all the studies
used FMD in combination with traditional
anti-cancer therapies. None that I'm
aware used FMD alone to combat cancer.
The second thing is to point out that
cancer is a diverse disease. So an FMD
isn't always going to be a good choice.
As one example, people with cexia, so an
involuntary weight and tissue loss from
cancer, may be in a poor position to use
an FMD. That said, discussing with your
oncologist and/or general physician is
important. And people usually comment,
"My physician doesn't know anything
about this stuff." And that's fair
enough because they have a lot to do.
But that doesn't mean that you can't
open the conversation with them. Your
physician shouldn't be shutting you down
or shutting these conversations down,
especially if you mention multiple
studies like we've been discussing up to
now. And to be clear, there is even
more. And finally, while we've been
focused on cancer in the context of
people who already have cancer, there's
plenty of signals indicating that FMD
can be preventative as well. So this
isn't limited to a small group of
individuals. It applies to many, even if
you don't have cancer. So then, how can
we implement a fasting mimicking diet?
Well, it's pretty simple. Like I
mentioned from the top, it's a 5-day
nutrition protocol. It's done every 21
to 28 days. So, at the longest, once per
month. The nutrition protocol consists
of this breakdown. Day 1 600 calories.
Day 2 through 4 is 300 calories. And the
macronutrient breakdown is 10% protein,
45% carbohydrates, and 45% dietary fat.
The nutrition is also plant-based. Like
I mentioned earlier, those numbers can
shift based on your metabolism. If you
want it to be calculated out for you,
for your personal situation, I offer
that for the insiders. The link is in
the description. Otherwise, this is the
easiest to remember. In total, that
leaves us with this understanding that a
fasting mimicking diet has clinical
evidence pointing to its effectiveness
in combating cancer. if you have it or
not. FMD does that through reducing
growth signals in the body along with
revitalizing our immune system and even
changing some cancer cells to become
anti-warberg against their nature among
other mechanisms. And for a large number
of cancers, there's fascinating evidence
that intravenous vitamin C could also
play a major role in eradicating cancer,
especially when paired with the fasting
mimicking diet. I go into more depth on
exactly that right here.